Guide to the Martin [Milton] Rackmil Memorabilia Collection MSS 073
Fales Library and Special Collections
Martin [Milton] Rackmil Memorabilia Collection
1938-1990
1953-1972
Fales Library and Special Collections
Rackmil, Milton R., 1906-1992
MSS 073
5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, and 7 flat boxes
5 sound discs (vinyl)
Milton R. Rackmil (1906-1992) was a native New Yorker and a New York University graduate. In 1934, Rackmil founded Decca Records with Jack Kapp and Edward Lewis, and became president in 1949. Decca Records became the largest shareholder in the Universal Pictures Company in 1951, and in 1952 Rackmil took over as president. MCA bought Decca and Universal in 1962 and Rackmil became vice chairman of MCA's board. He remained head of MCA's film and record companies until his retirement in 1972. This collection documents Rackmil's career in the music and film industries. Materials include scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, plaques, publicity, certificates, speeches, annual reports, correspondence, ephemera and five vinyl records dating from 1938 to 1990. The bulk of the collection focuses on memorabilia from Rackmil's time at Decca Records and Universal Pictures from 1938-1972.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1994.073.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in the order in which they were recieved from the donor.
Biographical / Historical
Milton R. Rackmil (1906-1992) was born in the Lower East Side of New York City. He grew up in Brooklyn and graduated from NYU with a degree in accounting. Rackmil worked for Brunswick Radio Corporation in the 1920s and helped form its record company subsidiary in the 1930s. In 1934, Rackmil founded Decca Records with Jack Kapp and Edward Lewis, and became president in 1949. Decca Records became the largest shareholder in the Universal Pictures Company in 1951, and in 1952 Rackmil took over as president. MCA bought Decca and Universal in 1962 and Rackmil became vice chairman of MCA's board. He remained head of MCA's film and record companies until his retirement in 1972.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
Materials include scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, plaques, publicity, certificates, speeches, annual reports, correspondence, ephemera and five vinyl records dating from 1938 to 1990. The bulk of the collection focuses on memorabilia from Rackmil's time at Decca Records and Universal Pictures from 1938-1972.
Separated Materials
One piece of rolled ephemera were removed for deaccession.
Decca Records (Firm); Universal Pictures (Firm); Rackmil, Milton R., 1906-1992
- Larry Evans and His Quartet [vinyl record], undated (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 1)
- Murray Arnold [vinyl record], undated (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 2)
- London Banquet in honour [sic] of the United States and Canadian distributors for the Decca Record Company Limited [vinyl record], 1964 (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 3)
- Dinner given by Mr. and Mrs. Eric Gallo to celebrate the 25th anniversary of the entry of Mr. E.R. Lewis into the Gramophone Record Industry [vinyl record], 1956 (Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 4-5)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Speech, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Certificates, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- MCA Merger, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Personal publicity, 1957-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 20th Anniversary, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 25th Anniversary, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 30th Anniversary (permanent) Decca Records, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Annual report and invoice, 1959, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Ephemera and photographs, 1962-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Certificate, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Memorandum, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Clippings, 1963-1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Draft report, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual meeting, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and contracts, 1951-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Letter [scrapbook], 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Milton Rackmil with wife Jackie (in Acapulco and N.Y.) [scrapbook], undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Pioneer Dinner Speech [scrapbook], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Pioneer Dinner photographs, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Around the World in 30 Days [scrapbook], 1953-09-11-1953-10-12 (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
- Personal Publicity, 1951-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Decca Records, Inc., 1938-1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Personal Publicity, 1954-1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- From Martin to Pres of U.I., 1956-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Photograph, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Decca Records, Inc., 1944 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- City Paper, 1984 (Box Shared Fales 004, Folder 7)
- Commemorative pen holder, 1962 (Box 5, Object 1)
- Commemorative glass plaque, 1964 (Box 5, Object 2)
- Award plaque, 1955 (Box 5, Object 3)
- Scrabooks, 1953-1962 (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Folder 1-2, Box 10)